CHAPTER 6

Mediations and the Body-Politic
The Problem of Representation Revisited

RATHEESH KUMAR

While introducing the concept of ‘ideological state apparatus’ towards building his thesis that ‘Ideology interpellates subjects’, Althusser (1971) writes:

Behind the scenes of its political-ideological state apparatus, which occupies the front of the stage, what the bourgeoisie has installed as its number-one, that is as its dominant Ideological State Apparatus, is the educational apparatus, which has replaced in its functions the previously dominant Ideological State Apparatus, the Church. One might then add: the school-family couple has replaced the church-family couple (145-6).

Here, Althusser presents an account of a replacement of institutional dominance in perpetuating the ideology of the bourgeoisie through the periods of the medieval to the modern. The Church-family couple gets replaced by the emergence of the modern education system as he attributes it as the school-family couple. If Althusser could rewrite this thesis in the twenty-first century, he would be considering the media-family couple replacing the school-family couple specifically when the schooling space itself is absorbed into the sphere of the media in the context of pandemic-enforced online pedagogy. Insofar as the mediascape expanded drastically with the emergence of the new media in its various guises, versions and platforms, the question of media representation and the subsequent social practices stem from and through its complex networks demand critical scrutiny. Taking media socialization to its centre, this chapter will focus on the questions of representation, gender and body politic in particular, towards a methodological concern beyond the domain of textuality.

The question of representation has always been central to the analyses of media texts, especially in the context of studying images of the body. Subjecting textual configurations towards unravelling body-politic in the context of analysing the ‘marginalized’ social groups remained to be a common track of approaching the problem of representation in contemporary media studies. This chapter takes a slight turn in its approach to the problem of representation and body politic by attempting a methodological realignment to underline the practices and effects that stem from text and its surroundings. This methodological shift in focus calls for a move from ‘what the text has’ to ‘what the text does’. As it is significant to track the containment of texts as the starting point to mapping the politics of representation, the question of underscoring signifying practices that stem from such textual representation is equally important to capture the problem in its totality (Hall: 1997). By selecting certain key sites of gendered and racialized bodies that represent marginality in particular domains of social hierarchy, the chapter traces the effects and practices those textual representations engender through their features and functions.

INTERFACING MEDIA, MARGINALITY AND
THE BODY-POLITIC

‘We live in a world that is media-saturated’, is one of the most frequently used phrases in today’s media discourses. In other words, no one can escape the effects that contemporary media, both old and new, have on our daily lives. In our social and personal interactions, the media wields tremendous power and influence. Individuals are exposed to a variety of media forms and contents. The exposure to media is significantly increasing in contemporary times as most individuals often get involved in watching videos, films either on the internet or television, reading blogs, newspapers, magazines, and listening to music, spending time on social media platforms, and all these activities are carried out, in most cases, through a single device, the smartphone. In the time of unprecedented mediation swept by the smart phone era, the frequent flash of notifications makes everyday life a constant site of distraction from routine tasks. As a result, as Virginia Wolf once aptly remarked that it is impossible to live outside the machine more perhaps than half an hour. A series of distracted and thus modified activities of the everyday create a social life that has yet to be explored to understand along with its mediating structures and agencies.

Now that we are aware of a variety of landscapes, regions and cultures, as well as the lives and experiences of individuals and communities who inhabit these constantly mediated landscapes (Knightley: 1975), Appadurai (1990) have translated the trajectories of such movements into the flow of mediascapes in the era of global cultural processes. Our world’s ‘culture epicentre’ has become the mass media, especially visual new media and television (Castells: 1996). The following section will examine the various elements of such mediations as they relate to mass communication, production and consumption of media contents in various forms and the critical connections that media offer between the concepts of body-politic and gendered and racist representations.

The power of media texts to represent ‘socially acceptable’ ways of being or relating to others becomes substantial, and their capacity to negotiate and produce public recognition, honour, and status for different sections of people is enormous. Cynthia Carter and Linda Steiner provide an account of the feminists fighting for egalitarian conceptions of womanhood in the 1860s in the United Kingdom and the United States. It demonstrates that newspapers and journals of the period derided or ignored women’s lived experiences to a great extent. Systematic research on media images of women flourished during the ‘second wave’ of the women’s movement in the 1960s. Feminist academics and activists began looking at how the objective of those critical reflections was to problematize the media enculturation through anti-women and sexist content that made hierarchical and binary sex-role stereotypes into ‘natural’ and ‘normal’.

In the 1970s, feminist studies took a critical turn by looking at how media portrayals bolstered the interests of the twin systems of patriarchy and capitalism. Gramsci’s (1971) concept of hegemony was a crucial and fertile concept underpinning this attempt to foreground the question of body politic in the whole affair of representation and participation in the media discourse. When the hegemonic and ideological modes of being, characteristic of the powerful groups are naturalized and made to appear ‘normal’, they are handed down to everyone as if there are no other answers, leading to a broader ‘common sense’. ‘The media play a critical role in gaining public consent’, Carter and Steiner accurately note. Instead of just reflecting or mirroring ‘reality’, media texts construct hegemonic beliefs about what constitutes ‘reality’ (Carter and Steiner: 2004). Representations in the media seem to be ‘real’ and commonsensical and therefore most often remain the taken-for-granted truths about social reality. As a result, media representations reflect the desires of powerful social groupings. Critical feminist studies argued that women fail, in most instances, to distinguish how patriarchal principles are culturally translated to look as ‘non-ideological’, ‘objective’, ‘natural’, and ‘non-gendered’. Although sex and gender are not identical, they are connected, chevaliers. Traditionally, the terms ‘sex’ and ‘gender’ have been used to refer to biological differences (male and female) and socio-cultural acquisitions of roles and behaviours (feminine and masculine) respectively. However, emergent debates on sexuality and identity have redefined gender and sex as a continuum rather than a fixed binary such as male/female or masculine/feminine (Butler: 1990).

The ideas about gender and sex are reconfigured constantly along the lines of socio-political, and historical contexts, and accordingly, those images in the media texts are subject to reception, which can, in effect, reproduce or counter-produce those modes of representation. Gender norms and relations are articulated in the media in significant ways. Both print and visual media, particularly television, are used to build fixed gender concepts through stereotyping. Though masculinity and femininity have diverse meanings in different cultures, media portrayals of these ideas tend to unify and standardize them in their representative patterns and meanings. Margaret Mead (1928) has long since written that what is seen as masculinity and femininity differs among cultures, based on her ethnographic investigations in Samoa and New Guinea. In other words, not only do various societies label certain traits as feminine and others as masculine, but these traits also differ among cultures and regions. As a result, feminists have objectively proved that there is no basic relationship between men’s and women’s biology and the qualities and behaviours that are considered masculine and feminine, respectively. In fact, the process of socialization has a significant bearing on molding children to comprehend such gender-specific forms of behaviour, attitude, mannerisms, clothing and so on. Socialization is frequently subtle, veiled, and functions at the ideological level. A variety of institutions socialize children, which designs the effects of bravery, aggression, and confidence as ‘masculine’ and modesty, sensitivity, and shyness as ‘feminine’, as equivalent to the value that society assigns to them, and the media play a key role in socializing girls and boys in distinct ways in terms of those norms and values.

One of the key subjects of concern is women’s position in the media sector and their level of participation. Several studies have discovered that women are assigned inferior positions and low-ranking employment in the media business around the world. Ann Ross Muir (1988) contends that if women are restricted to lower-paid and lower-status roles in the media sector, they will have fewer opportunities to influence content and representation and to combat gender stereotypes. She goes on to say that most television shows have a masculine perspective because men dominate and control the industry (Muir: 1988). Stott and Steiner note that, while working conditions for women journalists have improved significantly in recent decades, women have long been aware that many of their male colleagues doubted their capacity to produce ‘serious’ journalism simply because they were women. Some even claimed that every successful female journalist owed her success to her sexual availability (Carter and Steiner: 2004). Many journalists, editors, and producers across the world hold this skewed perspective.

When it comes to women in the television industry, most of the television industries around the world are dominated by men (UNESCO: 1987). It could reflect gender dynamics in other areas of life, when women are primarily confined to their homes. The gender configuration in the television industry was heavily influenced by this dominating cultural pattern, which was dominated by men. There were only a few women in prestigious positions of higher authority and power in the early days of television. In the last several decades, there have been certain improvements in the media sectors that have raised awareness about gender equality. Women now have a variety of options thanks to television. However, the generation of gender-sensitive material in media texts remains a critical subject. Is there a significant movement in gender stereotyping in television programming? It may be premature to see gender equality in the media because of the rise in female engagement in the field. In terms of describing gender equality, the relationship between patterns of employment within television organizations and television representations is situated differently. Then we must ask a critical question: what goes wrong if the presence of a greater number of women does not correlate to any major transformation in the organization of the programme’s content? According to statistics, women are unable to hold important decision-making roles in the majority of mass media businesses around the world. In the production of media content, van Zoonen’s work on feminism and journalism (1989) demonstrates a strong misalignment between institutional rules and individual objectives. Although feminist ethics were incorporated into their training, women journalists who advocated for them found it difficult to put their beliefs into practice in an institutional setting. Women tend to regard these tendencies as ‘normal’ and hence take them for granted because of ‘organizational socialization’.

STEREOTYPING BEYOND THE TEXT

In the study of media and culture, the concept of representation is one of the central concerns. ‘Representation’ or ‘to represent’ is a phrase used frequently in media studies to describe various methods of describing or presenting something for an audience to read or consume. Re-presentation allows mediation to reach the audience with diverse representations of the world, as an unmediated ‘actual world’ is not accessible. As a result, what we see on television, hear on the radio, or read in the newspaper will be a construction, involving decisions about content selection, camera positioning, editing, and so on.

Another approach to consider the issue of representation is how media images help us make sense of cultural symbols. This can lead to a better knowledge of how various social groups are frequently depicted in media texts, as well as how stereotyping of certain cultural groups and people occurs. As a result, media depictions can be viewed as a reflection of reality or as a distortion of something ‘real’ or ‘true’. This implies that we’re interested in determining how true media images are to reality, or how far the media misrepresents reality to maintain certain ideas. Media texts frequently fall into a regular kind of construction in their varied ways of representing the ‘actual’, which causes some social groups to become fixated; this is what we call the stereotyping process. Women, for example, are frequently shown or viewed in a narrow variety of roles, such as housewives, girlfriends, or secretaries, and in the case of some ethnic minorities, terrorists, criminals, or servants are frequently depicted (in the case of Muslims and Black people). Scholars contend that reversing stereotypes in a dramatic and immediate manner as part of media ethics will not achieve the desired result. This is due to the nuanced nature of the representation-reality interaction. What is genuine and what is representation are difficult to distinguish. So, to answer the question ‘Who represents whom?’ we must examine many examples of the production and dissemination of stereotypes.

In this context, Richard Dyer discusses the significance of examining the concept of ‘pleasure’ (Dyer: 1985). Who is getting pleasure out of experiencing a media text? Or what kind of pleasure a media text can offer by ways of representation and who is the target audience to those representations? Do audience members all get pleasure from media content in the same way? Given the social disparities in terms of colour, class, gender, ethnicity, and sexual orientation, it’s unlikely that all viewers, readers, and listeners will be equally comfortable with the styles of depiction. In the context of power and ideology, representations are created and transmitted in a social environment of meanings. This common sense of meaning is managed by authority, which elevates some meanings while demonizing others.

Stuart Hall poses a challenge that goes beyond the conventional view that representations are reflections or distortions of something real and instead asks whether occurrences in the universe have a single and essential fixed meaning that can be tested against distortion (Hall: 1997). In other words, reality does not have a fixed meaning until it is represented, and representations and their meanings fluctuate over time and location. What we call ‘reality’, according to Hall, does not exist outside of the process of representation; and the signs are always located in a dynamic relation to the production of meaning as they appear as ‘floating signifiers’ (Hall: 1997).

Correspondingly, the concept of sign was subject to a significant shift in the writings of postmodern and poststructuralist thinkers. Some of them were of the view that in the era of postmodernity, life is thrown into a sphere of mass-produced and massively disseminated media world, a storm of a set of complex signs. With the infinity of indicators in visual and new media texts that generate a ‘hyper-reality’, people struggle to distinguish reality from representation. The effects of stereotyping demand a revisit in the context of the emerging mediascape in the twenty-first century that includes the social media platforms in their constantly modified versions.

Stereotypes are a set of qualities that are assigned to individuals, groups, and civilizations fixedly. The word ‘typos’ comes from the Greek words ‘stereos’, which means ‘solid’, and ‘typos’, which means ‘mark’. The term was conceptually developed by Walter Lippmann, an early twentieth-century American journalist, in his work Public Opinion (Lippmann: 1922). Lippmann finds two crucial aspects of stereotypes. Firstly, stereotypes tend to be resistant to change; second, they generally carry a pejorative and narrow range of meanings (O’Sullivan et al.: 1994). As they are theoretically acknowledged, stereotypes often display a set of imprecise, but simplistic generalizations about individuals or groups or communities and cultures. Stereotypes and stereotyping are processes and products that relate to power and ideologies in each social milieu. As Tessa Perkins (1979) argues, stereotypes certainly display a set of existing social relations that may be partial, but not necessarily false in a complete sense. Therefore, the association between stereotypes and social reality is a complex one to draw straight-line conclusions. For example, portraying women in subordinate roles does not have to be read as a text that reproduces women’s inferior standing in society, as some critics say. Many cultural analysts, on the other hand, have suggested that media texts generate and perpetuate stereotypes, and there is evidence to back up this claim. In short, the mode of representation in which images constitute stereotypes, would not often be tantamount to the exact translation of those images towards reproducing them in the domain of reception.

Who creates stereotypical images of whom? This leads to a debate on who should represent the other. Who exactly is the other? ‘The other’ is the representative entity that is placed outside of one’s gender, race, class, religious, and ethnic identities. The building of the other, in most cases, turns out to be the construction of ‘the inferior other’ by society’s dominant individuals and organizations. How is stereotyping used to produce othering in media texts? What is the connection between stereotypes and the media? In the continuation or demotion of stereotypes, the media’s role in agenda-setting, gatekeeping, and ownership remains critical.

Grose examines the Sun Newspaper’s evident sex culture, which pervades every element of the publication, including the parts dedicated only to women. ‘The Sun termed its women’s pages packed with sex’, according to the paper’s interpretation of its history. They were made for women by women. However, they were dubbed ‘The pages for ladies that men can’t get enough of ’, implying that there are lots of things that captivate both men and women, such as sex (Carter and Steiner: 2004). Grose’s observation can be found in several magazines written by and for women. It demonstrates how women unwittingly participate in the creation of stereotypes. What messages are these publications attempting to convey to their readers? Women’s periodicals are often divided into two categories: those focused on homemaking and childcare, and those concerned with other topics.

The second type is involved with giving crucial marketing advice to attract a mate. This distinction creates a problematic dichotomy in which the first type of woman reflects the qualities of being homely, humble, chaste, maternal, and modest. The second type of woman, on the other hand, represents amoral, bold, sexual, sinful, and dangerous characteristics. Most Indian films include two female protagonists: a traditional ‘Indian woman’ who symbolizes the first group (and typically triumphs in the climax of the movie) and a modern/western woman who represents the second category, a sign of danger that threatens ‘Indian Culture’.

In her study on computer games, Heather Gilmour claims that most computer software now being made for girls reinforces hierarchical gender differences rather than challenging power structures. ‘Girls continue to be essentialized as emotional, highly social, modest, and soft-spoken while males are labelled as competitive and technologically inclined,’ she notes in most computer games (Gilmour: 2004). Chaudhuri explains the relationship between male supremacy in the industry and masculine ways of representation by looking at male domination in involvement and ownership in the mass media industry.

Exploring reality shows such as Who Wants to Be a Millionaire? Chaudhuri claims that women are less likely to apply, are less likely to be picked, and are less likely to win substantial awards. This finding is supported by the fact that most of these applications are created, presented, and assembled by men. Most of the questions asked in such contests are probably geared toward men. Female contestants may be treated differently than male contenders. She claims that, despite a rise in women’s employment and participation in the media industry, the sector’s larger culture remained masculinist, which eventually influenced the mode of representation and shaped content that was primarily masculine in nature (Chaudhuri: 1999).

Such gender distinctions are not based on any fundamental differences between boys and girls, but rather on the ‘ideologies and assumptions of researchers and developers’. Gilmour discovered that the disparities between male and girl gamers are mostly due to ‘cultural gendering of leisure and play’, rather than intrinsic biological variations, after surveying 180 students (90 boys and 90 girls) about their genre preferences. While game software makers treat females as a homogeneous, gendered group, girls’ game preferences and usage remain heterogeneous. Gilmour encourages computer scientists to think beyond traditional views of femininity as a monolithic category that unavoidably limits female behaviour, enjoyment and self-definition (Gilmour: 2004).

There is a broad pattern of stereotyping the image of the female protagonist in Indian Cinema industries, ranging from Bollywood to all south Indian industries. In Indian cinema, there is a trend toward homogenizing the physical look and mental attitudes of female leads. Men were considered as writers of true authentic literature—objective, and in control of their aesthetic methods, while women were seen as readers of ‘inferior literature, subjective, emotional, and passive’. It creates a double-edged process of sexualization and marginalization when it comes to women of colour or Dalit women (Rowena: 2012). It will be worthwhile tracing the feminist scholarship in its distinct strands while tracing the question of the representation of women and the question of body politic in contemporary media.

FEMINISM AND MEDIA STUDIES

For the past three to four decades, feminism has been without a doubt one of the most significant theoretical turns in academics, particularly in debates on media and culture. Feminism dominated media studies, seeking social change and continuing to reject male-dominated involvement and representation in the business. Feminism has become a ‘dirty’ word to some extent (particularly in male receptions) as a political and scholarly movement that continuously threatens the status quo. This is largely due to media misinterpretation of feminist principles. Furthermore, feminism has become divided in recent years (due to its inability to portray the variations amongst women (in terms of caste, class, race, ethnicity and sexuality) and has found itself under new criticisms and some of them perceived as ‘from within’ (Casey et al.: 2004). Feminism emphasizes gender as a large and crucial aspect of our cultural identity as a political, social, and academic movement as well as a theoretical approach. Gender is seen as a significant factor that shapes our physical and social environments. Various streams of feminist thought evolved at different historical junctures, each with its distinct viewpoints, such as Marxist, Liberal, Radical, black, and Dalit feminisms. However, at various degrees, they all claimed that men as a social group have treated women in a variety of unflattering ways in economic, political, educational, and social institutions. It’s worth noting that feminism has viewed patriarchy as more than just a case of men oppressing or discriminating against women. Patriarchy is established in our culture and social structures, according to feminism, and this could influence men’s conduct and views toward women. In terms of stereotyping women’s lives in the media texts and women’s engagement in the business, media as a powerful institution in shaping and expressing gender relations has also come under feminist scrutiny.

While early feminist concerns were on women’s lack of power in the media business, feminist interventions in the 1970s focused mostly on women’s limited representation and unfavourable stereotyping of their images and lives. Scholars such as Laura Mulvey introduced a new method of thinking about the gaze in the mid-1970s, focusing on spectator posture to see a film or television via male eyes—the male gaze thesis (Mulvey: 1975). The approach is based on the idea that the male gaze sexualizes women and turns them into mere sexual objects to be looked at. Here looking is understood to involve desire, control or desire to control. The male gaze is tangled up with the questions of power. Because stereotyping is not a simple and obvious phenomenon, feminist scholarship has recently begun to examine it more critically. The construction and representation of masculinity and masculine sexuality were also examined. The relationship between the second aspect and its impact on content and representation becomes a topic of contention. Male camera operators, directors, and producers have objectified women’s bodies and limited women’s range of positions.

Even though gender encompasses both men’s and women’s issues, the majority of critical writings and debates have focused on women’s experiences and portrayal until recently. Recent studies, on the other hand, have attempted to broaden the scope of gender and media studies by focusing on issues such as masculine sexualities, discourse, and representation of men. Men, in most media texts, inhabit a wider range of roles, that too in the public domains of occupation in the form of professionals, employers and labourers. They can be found in a wide range of ages, as well as different body types and vocal tones. Many studies of commercials and television shows imply that women are portrayed as domestic beings (as housewives or mothers) or as sexual objects or accessories to males in advertisements and television shows (bodies to sell products or assistants to powerful men).

The portrayal of older women is frequently associated with themes of cruelty and unkindness (as in the case of mother-in-law in Indian soap operas) or amusement. Women from ethnic minorities, particularly Dalit and dark-skinned women, are frequently presented as the ‘other’ and as ‘evil’ and ‘undesirable’ characters. In contrast, ‘typical’ femininity is overwhelmingly depicted as young, thin, tall, fair-skinned, and heterosexually domestic. On the other hand, ‘normal’ masculinity is often seen as less restricted and more often associated with action, power, authority and control. Matlin explains how the medium shapes reality, and how stereotyped depictions impact women’s perceptions of what they should look like. Girls and women frequently forget this and become overly sensitive to marketing (Carter and Steiner: 2004). We must analyse the contemporaneous and convergent meanings that advertising and their surrounding materials build and distribute about gender constitution as a whole.

TAKING ISSUES WITH THE ‘HOT’ CONTENT

Some scholars claim that internet spaces such as social networking sites like Facebook and Twitter, Instagram, personal blogs, and video-sharing sites like YouTube provide emancipatory potentials for excluded populations. The essential premise of this argument is that everyone could generate content that can challenge and oppose dominant and hegemonic images. However, most of the fields in these virtual places continue to contain anti-women, anti-Dalit, and racist rhetoric. For instance, if one types any (celebrity) woman’s name in the search box (of Google or YouTube), the topmost leading suggestions/options would be ‘hot’, ‘hot videos’, and ‘sexy’ after those women’s names. But this rarely happens in the case of their male counterparts. Social networking services like Facebook and Twitter have been a revelation in interacting with people, from the Arab Spring to the Anna Hazare campaign. Recently, a group of young people known as ‘change.org’, a social change portal, initiated an online campaign to remove sexually violent content from social networking sites such as Facebook. The study discovered that there is a lot of sexually aggressive information circulating in these virtual forums that makes women the mere objects of misogynic appropriation ((Young: 2000; Tejaswi: 2012). In the era of social media representations, overwhelming toxic content in the form of images and comments on the YouTube, Instagram and Facebook have become commonplace. In certain occasions, the intrusions in the form of stalking and bullying get extended to the real-life situations of violence, making a continuity to the idea of ‘following’ with a literal meaning of the term without the consent of the offended.

Robert Jenson investigates how the sexual charge is linked to the concept of male dominance and female submission which is important in contemporary commercial pornography by looking at visual spaces regarding sexual content and the making of pornography (Jenson: 2004).

He claims that whether a pornographer feels guilty or proud of his actions, the end consequence is the same: pornography continues to sexualize and objectify women, reducing them to simply sexual bodies for male enjoyment. As Jenson claims, pornography creates or reinforces desires for specific acts, most of which are focused on male pleasure and can cause female pain. Rather than unlocking sexual creativity, pornography shapes and constrains a person’s sexual imagination with its standardized scripts. Jenson also adds that race plays an important aspect in scripting pornography, which reinforces the view of women of colour as the ‘exotic primitive’.

For Jenson, the notion of authentic sexual desire is problematic; there is no pure, natural sexuality that is not mediated by culture. Here he simply contends that pornography is a force that can shape desire and that we should be concerned with how men may be conditioned to desire sexual acts that are humiliating, degrading and sometimes painful for women (Jenson: 2004). His observations on the interconnections of gender and race in the manifestation of body-politics in visual media necessitate a conceptual foundation, which can then shed light on the concept of pleasure in watching images of women of colour.

GAZE AND THE IDEA OF PLEASURE

In relation to studies on the domains of visual cultures, film, and television in particular, the male gaze has been a prominent topic of feminist intervention. Laura Mulvey’s psychoanalytical approach to the idea of the male gaze and pleasure in mainstream Hollywood movies opened new theoretical options in this argument (Mulvey: 1975). The works of Kaja Silverman, Teresa de Lauretis, Barbara Creed, bell hooks, and Ann Kaplin, among others, have recently sparked a substantial theoretical wave in the subject of feminist film theory (hooks: 1992; Kaplin: 2004; Mulvey et al.: 2006). Feminist interventions in the domain of television also gathered momentum in the works of Lila Abu-Lughod, Tania Modleski, Laura Stempel Mumford, Ien Ang, Deborah Jermyn and so on (Abu-Lughod: 1988; Akass & McCabe: 2006). However, feminist media criticism is never confined to the frame of simply focusing on the male gaze and the problem of representation.

bell hooks’ writings provided a fresh reading of the visual field against the usual trope of understanding gaze and representation from the viewpoint of the white feminist scholars. Contextualizing the idea of an oppositional gaze, hooks writes: ‘…the politics of slavery, of racialized power relations, were such that the slaves were denied their right to gaze. The “gaze” has been and is a site of resistance for colonized black people globally. Subordinates in relations of power learn experientially that there is a critical gaze, one that “looks” to document; one that is oppositional’ (hooks: 1992, 116). She goes on to say that stereotypically humiliating and dehumanizing depictions of blackness coexisted with a critical practice that restored presence where it had been lost. When the absence of black bodies in politically progressive film texts is replaced by their presence, stereotypes are often resurrected to fit into white viewers’ aesthetics, where victimization becomes a source of pleasure. This proclivity for depicting black bodies creates a barrier between the viewer and the image. ‘Black films were also subject to critical interrogation’, according to hooks, ‘as they came into being in part as a response to white-dominated cinema’s failure to represent blackness in a way that did not reinforce white supremacy, they too were critiqued to see if images were seen as complicit with dominant cinematic practices’. hooks goes on to say that black women’s long silence as observers and critics was a reaction to absence, to cinematic denial (ibid.: 117-18).

The question of denial and absence that the cinematic space presents for coloured women, as expressed in the framework of hooks, may be applied to understanding how ‘caste bodies’ are represented in Indian mainstream cinema, particularly Bollywood. When it comes to the critical literature on body politics, however, the topic of women’s presence and representation arises at the level of problematizing the sexualized bodies of upper caste/fair-bodied women. Concerns about what happens to the bodies of women of colour when their photographs are transmitted in a sphere of spectatorship that is largely influenced by the notions of caste and untouchability, as well as masculine gaze. Jenny Rowena’s account of Silk Smitha’s biopic The Dirty Picture (Dir. Milan Luthria 2011), tackles this tricky context of body-politic and the caste question imprinted in cinematic texts where the idea of sexuality and visual pleasure are subject to scrutiny through a different vantage point (Rowena: 2012). Rowena’s critique enables us to broaden the frame of oppositional gaze within the context of caste, not prompting us to settle easily within the binaries of the victim or the perpetrator. Drawing from hooks (1992) and reading through Rowena (2012), I argue that the Black and therefore the Dalit-Bahujan female spectators, who refuse to identify with white/upper caste womanhood, who would not settle with the idea of phallocentric gaze of desire and possession, but attempt to craft a critical space where the binary opposition that Mulvey offers—‘woman as image, man as bearer of the look’—gets continually deconstructed.

Recognizing the presence of black and Dalit female audiences would open a conceptual space for discussing pleasure politics in the context of the dissemination of pictures of coloured bodies. Relocating representational arguments from within the text to the practices that texts produce during their circulation would allow for a more critical analysis. According to hooks, mainstream feminism has made little attempt to investigate the idea that women can develop an opposing perspective through a better understanding and awareness of race and racist politics. ‘Feminist film theory, rooted in an ahistorical psychoanalytic framework that privileges sexual difference, actively suppresses recognition of race, reenacting and mirroring the erasure of black womanhood that occurs in films, silencing any discussion of racial difference—of racialized sexual difference.’ Her claims substantiate the fact that grotesque bodies carry different histories and biographies (hooks: 1992, 122). This necessitates a methodological shift toward documenting subaltern women’s spectatorial experiences to comprehend concerns of representation and body politics from a contrasting perspective to mainstream feminist concepts.

As against the survey model of reception studies, there is a growing demand towards micro-social histories to be constructed through the methods of critical ethnography and historical anthropology (Lughod: 2006). Instead of relying on the narrow idea of reception in a quantitatively naïve manner, it is imperative to have accounts of media experiences of individuals beyond the textual aspects of representation. How media generate new ways of organizing daily life for different groups of people especially in the time of new media platforms and gadgets invites critical attention from emerging scholars. Daniel Miller’s account on Facebook communities in Trinidad and Tobago would throw light on such a critical scholarly endeavour beyond the textual domain of media and enter the contours of practice through ethnographic explorations (Miller: 2010). To conclude, it is evident from the above discussions that representations of gender and gendered bodies are neither simple nor the audience readings of the text are rather complex and multi-dimensional, and critical scrutiny cannot limit its analytical scope within the text, but to engage with what kinds of practices that texts generate as social practices.

REFERENCES

Abu-Lughod, Lila (1986). Veiled Sentiments: Honour and Poetry in a Bedouin Society, Berkley: University of California Press.

Adorno, T. (1991). The Culture Industry: Selected Essays on Mass Culture, London: Routledge.

Althusser, L. (1971). Lenin and Philosophy and Other Essays. London: New Left Books.

Akass, K. & McCabe, J. (2006). ‘Feminist Television Criticism: Notes and Queries’, Critical Studies in Television, vol. 1, no. 1, pp. 108-20.

Appadurai, Arjun (1990). ‘Disjuncture and Difference in the Global Cultural Economy’. Theory, Culture and Society, Sage, 7: 295-310.

Askew, K. and Wilk, R. (2002). The Anthropology of Media: A Reader, USA: Blackwell.

Benedict, R. (1946). The Chrysanthemum and the Sword Patterns of Japanese Behaviour, Boston: Houghton Mifflin.

Bathla, S. (2008). ‘Gender Construction in News Media’, in Marie John (eds.), Women Studies in India—A Reader, New Delhi: Penguin Books.

Butler, J. (1990). Gender Trouble: Feminism and the Subversion of Identity, London and New York: Routledge.

Carter, C. and Steiner, L. (2004). Critical Readings: Media and Gender, UK: Open University Press.

Casey, B. et al. (2004). Key Concepts in Television Studies, London and New York: Routledge.

Castells, M. (1996). The Rise of Network Society. Oxford: Basil Blackwell.

Chaudhuri, A. (1999). ‘Who wants to be a quiz show contestant?’, Guardian, 29 November.

Dyer, Richard (1985). ‘Taking Popular Television Seriously’, in D. Lusted and P. Drummond (eds.), TV and Schooling, London: BFI.

Geer, G. (1970). The Female Eunuch, UK: Harper Perennial.

Geertz, C. (1973). The Interpretation of Culture, New York: Basic Books.

Gilmore, Heather (2004). ‘What Girls Want: The Intersections of Leisure and Power in Female Computer Game Play’ in C. Carter and L. Steiner (eds.), Critical Readings: Media and Gender, UK: Open University Press.

Gramsci, A. (1971). Selection from the Prison Notebooks, London: Lawrence and Wishart.

Hall, Stuart (1981). ‘The Whites of Their Eyes: Racists Ideologies and the Media’, in G. Bridges and R. Brunt (eds.), Silver Linings: Some Strategies for the Eighties, London: Lawrence and Wishart.

——. (1997). Representation: Cultural Representations and Signifying Practices, London, New Delhi: Sage/Open University Press.

hooks, bell (1992). Black Looks: Race and Representation. Boston: South End Press.

Jeffrey, R. (2010). Media & Modernity, New Delhi: Permanent Black.

Jenson, R. (2004). ‘Knowing Pornography’, in C. Carter and L. Steiner (eds.), Critical Readings: Media and Gender, Maidenhead: Open University Press.

Joseph, A. and Sharma, K. (1994). Whose News? The Media and Women’s Issues, New Delhi: Sage.

Kaplan, E. (2004). ‘Global Feminisms and the State of Feminist Film Theory.’ Signs, 30(1): 1236-48. doi:10.1086/421879.

Knightley, P. (1975). The First Casualty: The War Correspondent as Hero, London: Deutsch.

Lippmann, W. (1922, republished 1965). Public Opinion, New York: Free Press.

Mead, M. and Bateson, G. (1942). Balinese Character: A Photographic Analysis, New York: New York Academy of Sciences.

McQuail, D. (1994). Mass Communication Theory, London: Sage.

Miller, D. (2010). Tales from Facebook. London: Polity Press.

Millett, K. (1970). Sexual Politics, London: Abacus.

Moore, H. (1988). Feminism and Anthropology, USA: University of Minnesota Press.

Mulvey, Laura (1989). ‘Visual Pleasure and Narrative Cinema’, Visual and Other Pleasures. London: Macmillan.

O’Sullivan, T., Hartley, J., Saunders, D., Montgomery, M. and Fiske, J. (1994). Key Concepts in Communication and Cultural Studies. London: Routledge.

Otner, S. (1972). ‘Is Female to Male as Nature is to Culture?’, in Woman, Culture and Society, edited by M.Z. Rosaldo and L. Lamphere. Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press, 67-87.

Perkins, Tessa (1979). ‘Rethinking Stereotypes’, in M. Barrett et al. (eds.), Ideology and Cultural Production, London: Croom Helm.

Powdermaker, H. (1950). Hollywood: The Dream Factory. An Anthropology Looks at the Movie Makers, Boston: Little Brown.

Rowena, Jenny (2012). ‘The “dirt” in The Dirty Picture: Caste, Gender and Silk Smitha.’ In Round Table India. https://roundtableindia.co.in/index.php?Itemid=132&catid=119%3Afeature&id=5283%3Athedirt-in-the-dirty-picture-caste-gender-and-silk-smitha&option=com_content&view=article (Last accessed on 12 October 2010).

Tejaswi, A. (2012). ‘Youths Fight it out Online’, Deccan Chronicle, 19 April, 17-19.

UNESCO (1987). Women and Decision Making: The Invisible Barriers, Paris: UNESCO.

van Zoonen, L. (1989). ‘Professional Socialization of Feminist Journalists in the Netherlands’, Women’s Studies in Communication, 12(3): 1-23.

Young, M. (2002). Sexuality and the Internet. Science as Culture. 11(2): 215-33.

List of Contributors

MANOJ KUMAR JENA is Professor of Sociology and Chairperson at the Study of Social Systems, School of Social Sciences, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi. He is the coordinator of the International Global Studies Programme of JNU, New Delhi. He has also coordinated an International Collaborative Teaching Programme with the Department of Sociology, York University, Canada. He also taught in the Department of Sociology, Jamia Millia Islamia, New Delhi. His areas of research interests are: Sociology of Science and Technology, Digital Technology Studies, Media Studies, and Ritual Studies. His writings hve appeared in many national and international peer-reviewed journals. His recent publications include Sociology of Covid 19 Pandemic in India: Education, Digital Divide, Work and Wellbeing (ed.) (2022) and Ways of Being Indian: Essays on Religion, Gender and Culture (ed.) (2024).

RENUKA SINGH is a former Professor of Sociology at the Centre for the Study of Social Systems, School of Social Sciences, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi. She has been working in the area of Gender Studies, Diaspora, and Buddhist Studies for over four decades, and travels extensively delivering lectures at various seminars and universities. She has been associated with the Women’s Studies Centre, University of Delhi, Centre for Social Research, and was a Research Fellow at Centre for Cross-Cultural Research on Women at Oxford University. She is currently the Director of Tushita Mahayana Meditation Centre, New Delhi, and the Chairperson of Punjabi Sahitya Sabha, New Delhi. She has authored and edited several articles and books that have been translated into many languages of the world. Some of the titles are: The Womb of Mind, Women Reborn, The Path to Tranquility, The Transformed Mind, Many Ways to Nirvana, The Path of the Buddha, Becoming Buddha, Dalai Lama’s Little Book of Buddhism, Dual Identity: Indian Diaspora and Other Essays, Boundless as the Sky, Dalai Lama’s Little Book of Mysticism, The Little Book of Encouragement, and The Greatest Punjabi Stories Ever Told.

M.M. REHMAN is a former Senior Fellow at V.V. Giri National Labour Institute, Noida. He holds PhD degree in Economics. He worked at the National University of Educational Planning and Administration, (formerly, National Institute of Educational Planning and Administration). He extensively worked on issues such as informal sector workers, women workers, and social security of workers. He has conducted action research/research and number of evaluation studies on different fields related to education and labour. He also conducted a substantial number of training programmes for different groups comprising officials and activists. He has published several books and research monographs on topics related to education, jobholders in the informal sector, social security of workers, etc.

KANTA REHMAN holds a Ph.D in Political Science. She is the author of several books on human rights. She has worked in several organizations and institutions designated for research and education. She was initially an active community organizer and worked among the marginalized sections of the society. She has also done a lot of work in the field of action research for slum dwellers and has set up various informal schools.

KURUKHETRA DIP is an Assistant Professor of Sociology at the Department of Sociology, Faculty of Social Sciences, Banaras Hindu University. He previously taught at the Department of Sociology, Maa Manikeshwari University (formerly, Kalahandi University). His research areas include disability studies, cinema studies, sociology of health, and visual anthropology. He has completed his MA, M.Phil., and Ph.D. from Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi. Currently, he is serving as a board member (Board of Directors) of the Society for Disability Studies (SDS).

NESHAT QUAISER is an Associate Researcher with the Centre de Sciences Humaines (CSH), Delhi. He was the former Professor and Head of the Department of Sociology, Jamia Millia Islamia, Central University, Delhi. His research interests include: Critical Social Theory; Historical Sociology of Indian sub-continental medical traditions with a specific focus on Unani medicine; Muslims, Islam, Sharia, and Communalism in Indian sub-continent; Culture Religion and Society; Historical Sociology of Urdu language and literature; Colonialism and colonial politics; Post-Colonial Law and Legal Theory; Religion, Nationalism, and Peasant Politics in Indian subcontinent with the reference to Muslim politics and society; and inter-religious public debate during the colonial period.

RATHEESH KUMAR works as an Associate Professor at the Centre for the Study of Social Systems, School of Social Sciences, Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi, India. He has previously taught at the Department of Anthropology, University of Hyderabad and at the School of Interdisciplinary and Trans-disciplinary Studies, Indira Gandhi National Open University (IGNOU), New Delhi. He was a Charles Wallace India Trust Visiting Fellow at the Centre for Research in Arts, Social Sciences and Humanities (CRASSH), University of Cambridge (2021-2022). His recent publications include the coedited volume, Practising Interdisciplinarity: Convergences and Contestations (2024).

BISWAJIT DAS is the Professor and founding Director of Centre for Culture, Media and Governance. He has over four decades of teaching and research experience in the field of theory, method, and history of communication in India. He has published in various national and international journals. He is also the founding President of All India Communication and Media Association in India. His publications include Media and Mediation (2005), Social and the Symbolic (2007), Communication, Culture and Confrontation (2010), Gandhian Thought and Communication (ed.) (2020), and Caste, Communication and Power (ed.) (2021). His latest publications are: Seeing South Asia: Visuals beyond Borders (ed.) (2022), Korean Wave in South Asia: Transcultural flow, fandom and Identity (ed.) (2022) and Pedagogy in Practice: Project-Based Learning in Media policy & Governance(ed.), (2022).

RIDHI KAKKAR is a Research Scholar and Teaching Assistant at the Ashank Desai Centre for Public Policy, Indian Institute of Technology-Bombay. She has earned her M.A. and M.Phil. in Media Governance from the Centre for Culture, Media & Governance, Jamia Millia Islamia, New Delhi. She takes an interest in media and communication research. Currently, she is pursuing her PhD degree in the area of data governance and issues related to its monetization, access, and usage.

SHRUTI DEVGAN is an Assistant Professor of Sociology at Bowdoin College, USA. She holds a Ph.D. in Sociology from Rutgers University, USA. Her research interests include transnational flows, collective memory, trauma, narratives, media, Asian and American studies. She is currently working on a book on the digital, diasporic, and intergenerational memories of the anti-Sikh violence of 1984.

BINU SUNDAS is an Assistant Professor, Department of Sociology, Miranda House. Before joining Miranda House, he was teaching at Sikkim University. He is one of the founders of Sikkim University. He is also a Visiting Faculty at the Indian Institute of Management, Rohtak. He has authored two books, co-authored a book, and has many publications to his name. He has also presented many research papers at national and international conferences and seminars. He is an alumnus of Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi and Goethals Memorial School, Kurseong. He was also a football player of repute, and represented North Bengal University and he also played in the Calcutta League.

DIVYA PRADHAN is an Associate Professor, Department of English, Mata Sundri College for Women. She has many publications to her name and has presented many papers in international and national seminars and conferences. Her areas of interest are Indian Writing in English and Indian Philosophy. She is an alumnus of Jawaharlal Nehru University, New Delhi.